Guide to the Coleman family papers, 1895-1971
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Coleman family papers 1895-1971
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Coleman family.
3.0 linear feet Extent: Approx. 364 Items
Residents of Canada, Europe, and Asheville, N.C. Collection consists largely of a two-volume diary, 1895-1919, of Isabel Fleury Coleman, a twenty-three volume set of diaries, 1904-1971, belonging to Mary Augusta Coleman, and photographs of Fleury-Coleman family members and some of their residences. There are also two volumes pertaining to Mary Coleman's personal accounts and the "French Broad River Garden Club, 1967-1969," a few items of correspondence and genealogy, and a number of clippings and printed materials. Topics covered by the materials include music instruction (violin and piano), women's society life in Asheville, N.C., and women's travel in European countries during the 20th century.
RL.00259
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Coleman family papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a Flowers Collection purchase in 1980 from an unknown source.
Biographical Note
The two daughters whose materials are predominant in this collection, Isabel and Mary Augusta, were born to Rufus Adams Coleman and Clara Elma Fleury Coleman. It appears from a business card that Mr. Coleman was an attorney and conveyancer in Toronto. He disappeared from their lives and does not seem to be referred to much in the collection, not even in his wife's obituary. Mrs. Coleman's parents, the Fleurys, were from Aurora, Ontario. Mrs. Coleman and her daughters Isabel, Mary, and Helen lived for a time in Toronto, then Germany. Isabel and Mary studied music extensively in Leipzig; Mrs. Coleman was an accomplished pianist and her daughter Mary a violinist. The family then moved to Berlin, then to Switzerland, after which they moved to England during World War I. They also seem to have lived in France and Italy. Mrs. Coleman and Mary Augusta lived in Europe for over 25 years. Isabel returned to the U.S. to work as a governess and was living in Asheville when her mother and sisters moved there in 1923. Mary and Isabel both taught in Asheville and were very active in upper-class social circles to which they belonged. The other sister Helen appears to have remained in Canada and may have been in the Weston Sanatorium, from a reference in a letter written by Isabel.
Collection Overview
Collection consists largely of a two-volume diary, 1895-1919, of Isabel Coleman, a twenty-three volume set of diaries, 1904-1971, belonging to Mary Augusta Coleman, and photographs of Fleury-Coleman family members and some of their residences. There are also two volumes pertaining to Mary Coleman's personal accounts, "French Broad River Garden Club, 1967-1969," a few items of correspondence and genealogy, and a number of clippings and printed materials. Topics covered by the materials include music clubs, instruction and performance (violin and piano) in Europe and the U.S., women's society life and fashions in Asheville, N.C., and women's travel in European countries during the 20th century. There are few comments about current events, even during the World Wars and the Depression, but there are extensive accounts of social life and customs in Europe and Asheville, N.C.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Coleman family (N.C.); Fleury family; Music -- Instruction and study; Pianists -- United States; Violinists -- United States; Women travelers; Women -- Diaries; Women -- Societies and clubs -- North Carolina -- Asheville; Europe -- Description and travel; Europe -- Social life and customs -- 20th century; Asheville (N.C.)--Social life and customs; Asheville (N.C.)--History; Diaries -- Travel; Diaries; Photographs
Contents of Collection
- Coleman Family papers, 1895-1971, (4 boxes)
  - Volumes
    - Diaries of Isabel Fleury Coleman, 1895-1919 (Box 1)
    - Diaries of Mary Augusta Coleman, 1904-1924 (Box 1)
    - Accounts, etc. (Box 1)
    - Diaries of Mary Augusta Coleman, 1924-1971 (Box 2)
  - Other Papers
    - Correspondence, 1909-1960 (Box 3)
    - Addresses and Writings, 1905-1912 (Box 3)
    - Genealogy (Box 3)
    - Clippings (Box 3)
    - Pictures, (Includes portraits and family photos) (Box 4)